welcome to meditating with John barbecue
we live stream every weekday morning at
9:30 a.m. Eastern Time Mondays the
alternate between a dharma day in which
i teach it a lesson and a pi day in
which I rule you the entire ecology of
practices if you're joining us for the
first time welcome and the description
for this video you'll find links to
previous lessons and sets I recommend
going immediately to lesson 1 going
through that come back you can sit with
us every day and then every Saturday or
Sunday do another one of the lessons and
then eventually you'll be fully caught
up with us I would like to ask
everybody's help in raising the
visibility of this video stream on
YouTube by liking it helped me to reach
as many people as possible please at the
end of every set we have a QA please
limit the questions to this course this
ecology of practices for more
encompassing questions every third
Friday of the month at 3 p.m. Eastern
Time live stream a general Q&A on
YouTube the soul would like to make an
announcement again is to remind
everybody that down the road we're going
to be going through this book together
the wisdom of Hypatia by Bruce Lee
McClellan and I've been told you can get
it on Kindle that's the book that you'll
need I want to say mandatory as if it
was a course but are we required as we
as we go through the Western wisdom
tradition I want to also recommend this
book by Pierre hadou what is ancient
philosophy so this is a book to study so
that you can get a little bit this is a
very accessible beautifully written book
that really emphasizes the wind that
ancient Western philosophy Greek
philosophy especially was about the
cultivation of wisdom and it's an
excellent supplement and it will provide
there
useful and important background for the
course the wisdom of Hypatia a reminder
again the that what we're doing here is
you're not going to be doing all of
these practices right that's not the
point the point is to give you an
educated exposure and then can you
design principles we've talked about
those principles of complementarity
principles of layering principles of
linking and the general areas in which
you want to have developed practices and
then we want to draw on these two major
streams each has variation within it the
Western stream that has its variations
between you know Platonism Aristotelian
ISM and stoicism and Epicureanism and
the UH platonism of course the Eastern
tradition that has various forms of
Buddhism and Taoism and Vedanta and
Confucianism so you want to draw alright
on both of these as much as we can so
that we have a principled pluralism in
an ecology of practices all right so I
think that's all the announcements we
need to make we're going to do a regular
sitting today normally we have a heart
out to ten we can do a little bit longer
today but we will but in sort of
compensation we will have a harder
tomorrow right at ten so we will try and
answer a few more questions today so
please get yourself in your basic
posture set your phones to do not
disturb and we will begin oh one more
announcement I will review the seated
shiquan practices again tomorrow
okay so set your phones or do not
disturb
and we will begin together when I say
begin
yeah
Shh slowly come on up you practice
trying as best you can to integrate with
your cultivated in your practice with
your everyday consciousness cognition
character and communitas perhaps by
reciting the five promises to yourself
[Applause]
so just one more note with the physician
philosophy by Pierre hadou as soon as
you get this book you could begin
reading it so we have one question today
so far from Lawrence fulvic I have
started to write notes after doing let's
see a Davina on particular thoughts or
insights that may come to me is this a
good idea and would it be considered
part of watering my Buddha it's a good
idea and that's exactly what it is
sorry I don't have a really you know
expansive answer for you because it is a
good idea and it would be and that as a
way to water your Buddha very much they
mean to mean
make sure that you're maintaining the
right relationship to this it right so
that the Buddha isn't a possession it's
not something you have something you're
becoming it is right to be aspired to
within the being mode so as long as
you're framing it that way I think
that's an excellent suggestion and an
excellent practice to engage it and
there's a way in which if you take that
into the logos some of those insights
that getting into that dialogical
insight way of inhabiting your mind and
your body and your world is very
conducive to going deeply into the logos
practice you have another question from
manual post I've got a tendency to go
tense over time while meditating any
tips so there might be a few things
going on there it might be that you're
encountering some anxiety and if it's
sort of expressing in that way
you may be you may want to talk to
somebody about some potential background
anxiety you have it may be that you're
trying too hard and so the right effort
is not there it's very much right that's
why that's why these are the practices
and remember when we're doing the
standing practices like when we're doing
the Gen John or when we're doing the
moving practices each one as part of as
as part of the Chacon remember they were
trying to get pum right it's a lip but
it's not tense and you could practice
getting hung in your body and you can
think about that in connection to that
state in and it sort of plugs into being
centered and routed when you're routed
you are you are sensitive you're relaxed
but you're also highly alert so I would
have to do more work if you started
getting tense first you can direct meta
towards the tension or direct the five
factors of acquiring mindfulness you may
want to reroute at least do the opening
the expanding and Reese entering to
reroute and you may try to remember what
Poong feels like in the standing
practices and that that's a that's a
it's a home for your body in your in
your seat to practice it so that might
help like I say I don't know you and
there might be some deeper issues that
as your consciousness is starting to
light up parts of the mind that nor are
normally dark it might be coming to the
surface that I don't know and that I
don't have any expertise or even right
to talk to you about that here other
than if that if you have a sense if when
I say that there's an intuitive sense
that that might be right and if if and
again I don't want to be presumptuous if
you know time and finances for this you
might
talk to somebody about why you might be
carrying around some background levels
of anxiety but first I'll try the other
practices that I emphasized and they may
help you deal with that sort of
background tension you may just be
carrying around a lot and we all do on a
body armor and so learning to rien habit
your body and your mind and your body
and if you play and remember what it's
like when you're sitting when your seats
seated can be very helpful karema has a
question below crema and progeny I was
exhale in on the other breath now with
the our breath and the newest transition
my breath wants to ship but it's not
comfortable suggestions so well try the
shift and see if you can do some 5
factors on the discomfort what's the
nature of the discomfort is there is
there a habit that's being challenged or
is it uncomfortable in that perhaps it
is too energetic for you I would if
there's a part that wants to shift try
the shift and then when the discomfort
is coming up trying directing the five
factors of encoring mindfulness towards
it and try directing Mehta towards it
and see what's going on there because
there's something that's wanting to
explore what this will do for you and
there's something in you that doesn't
want to and it's of course unclear which
one right probably neither one of them
exclusively so you're trying to get some
sort of get them to talk to each other
more readily and don't try and force the
solution sort of stay with it and live
with it get the two to talk to each
other and hopefully you'll get a
resolution that self-organizes out of
that tone us out of that our creative
tension that will actually be deeper for
you than before you went into the
tension
Martha Feb hi mark always great to hear
from you what practices went can we do
to help with our inner critic how do we
be less hard on ourselves
so the practice that was mentioned
earlier I forget the name of the person
who suggested I'm sorry but writing down
your insights watering your Buddha you
if you just try to counter argue the
critic that will only exacerbate it you
can direct Mehta towards it you can
listen to the voice of the critic you
can do all that that you're no doubt
practicing and that will help
disidentify you to summit degree with
the critic you also want to get
basically a counter active us us
aspiring sense of the presence of the
Buddha you're in a mood out your teacher
because that will tend to challenge the
presence of the inner critic so I find
is requiring mindfulness especially
trying to get at the voice disidentify
from it listen to the silent moments
within the inner criticism also direct
matter towards it's coming from trying
to appreciate the ways in which it's
been adopted for you but also to open up
more to it's more or less and it's such
an us but also cultivating regularly
outside of the confrontation watering
your inner Buddha trying to strengthen
that felt presence that aspiring
presence because that will also counter
man and counteract our the presence of
the inner critic and what has tended to
happen is they tend to for me they've
tended to slowly do this kind of thing
uh-huh
notice the language is feeling me they
sort of do this which they almost like a
chemicals coming into reaction and
shifting and shaping and combusting and
something new and different comes out of
it so that's what I would recommend for
that Lou quest I manage depression
moderately well on a cognitive
behavioral therapists and have my
supervisor but what a thought it makes
the month
and extremely strong beanie ideas so
this is where and I'm going to keep
teaching you more of these this is where
the moving practices are very very
helpful you probably know our behavioral
therapists that exercise in general and
mindfulness in general is very helpful
but getting in a moving practice
especially to get the cerebellum frontal
cortex loop activated and more
dynamically self-organizing can very
much help with with wrestling with
depression you might actually try going
for a walk then doing the moving
practices and then going into the sit of
the seated practices I also recommend
you are doing the cognitive behavioral
therapy so you have reframing techniques
I would also recommend sort of
incorporate sort of expanding out and
them out
we situating the CBT back into its
ancient heritage home which of course is
stoicism you might want to start reading
some stoicism there's many books on how
to practice stoicism and the very things
you various things you do so you could
sort of take the CBT and expand it in
into stoicism with a set of accompanying
and more encompassing practices and then
as I said you could for the more
immediate wrestling you could build in
more exercise and especially the moving
mindfulness practices other cheek own
practices that should be helpful to you
our open Kelly Meyers further to see you
again Kelly I started noting whenever I
open my eyes and seeing last week your
comments yesterday about moving hand
positions as the sneaky way of monkey
might make me think to apply the same
noting approach to fidgeting and itching
as moving am I taking the noni concept
too far here no I think that's good I
think that that that's yeah that's very
the monthly yeah yeah I'm sorry I'm the
the familiarity of of the impishness of
the monkey mind it was it was coming to
mind and I guess I've developed a kind
of
a bit of amusement from that familiarity
yeah so there's all kinds of ways in
which the monkey mind insinuates itself
into your practices in that way well and
as long as you feel that you're not
getting harsh and prickly and you know
sort of you're sort of dissecting to
death your experience with the noting
that it sounds to me like what you're
because remember we're always for
education never like never sure
asceticism or pure endurance fear but
sums to me like that's not happening to
you and if that's not happening to you I
think what you're suggesting doing
within with the extension of the noting
practice I think is is a really good
idea try it out I think it will be
beneficial to you at least I hope it
well like I said just make sure you're
not getting into that right because then
then we're losing the middle path so
thank you all for joining it's always a
great pleasure and I appreciate
participating in this segment I want to
thank my dear friend Anna Technovation
Mar for all of his work that he's doing
behind the scenes my beloved son who's
always here coping with contingencies
helping me with the SAP please subscribe
to this channel to be notified of the
next video on the channel you'll find
links to the lecture series awakening
for the meaning crisis and to the
dialogo series voices with Rob a key in
which these ideas these themes these
practices and more encompassing way of
life as being are being developed and
explored in connection with that there
is the discord server where there is a
growing vibrant and really life-giving
community for Brett is here pleasure of
doubt they they meet before this set
they do the moving practices they sit
and then sometimes go two legs here
sometimes into deal logos or to other
practices and then there's just a more
encompassing community there every
second Monday I'm there doing a live QA
many of the people from voices for
baekje I go on I'm do just wonderful QA
so I strongly recommend going on to the
discord server
a reminder that we are doing this every
weekday morning at 9:30 Eastern Time
finally remember that continuity of
practice is more important than sheer
quantity of practice there is no enemy
worse than your own mind and body
there is no friend no allied no true
companion on the path greater than arrow
and minded buddy be lamps unto yourself
and to each other
take good care everyone I'll see you
tomorrow